Introduction

“The only way to discover the limits of the possible is to go beyond them into the impossible.”

-- Arthur C. Clarke

In our world, the word “impossible” has real meaning. Some things can happen, though they might be very improbable. Other things simply cannot. This may feel smothering, but unbreakable laws of nature are honestly pretty great. Our world’s limits provide us a place to live: a tiny interface between crushing pressure and harsh vacuum. If all things were possible, many of those things would not be the least bit beneficial to humanity.

However, Sorcerously Advanced is not a scientific universe, and the people there are nowhere near discovering the limits of their magic - if it even has limits.

In that spirit, let us venture a bit beyond what has been possible and stretch toward the impossible, to see what it has in store for us.

This book is broken into five chapters:

The New Expressions chapter introduces about a dozen new spells for your characters to discover. Some are well-known throughout the Basin, but most are recently recovered by the Archive - or, depending on your GM’s plans, soon to be recovered.

Mystical Infrastructure gives more detail on Infrastructure-level Expressions, including commonly-used techniques for diverting flow, devastating environmental attacks, and ways to hide entire nations from observation.

In The Broken and the Lost we cover two kinds of archaic magic: failed attempts to create Grand Wonderworks, and specialized Arts that have fallen out of use over the centuries.

Living with Magic talks about what Nature scores really mean, how changing your Tradition works in-universe, and a little bit of what it’s like to live with the constant influence of magic in each Civilization.

Finally, the Useful References chapter includes a list of spells categorized by descriptor (Connection, Loud, or Silent), and lists of suggested aspects for each Expression.

The Broken and the Lost

Broken Technologies

The five Grand Wonderworks described in Sorcerously Advanced are not the only technologies created by long-lost civilizations. The four-billion-year history of the Basin provides vast numbers of such marvels. Unfortunately, most of them are badly broken.

Concordance Beacons [Statecraft]

On one continent, eleven glimmering beams of light pierce the skies. They are placed about fifty koss apart from one another, and each is visible for a hundred koss or more in every direction. By focusing on the beam, you may sense any other people who are likewise looking at one of the beacons and rapport with them (assuming they are willing). Unlike the normal peace of Rapport, the beacons’ flickering light causes headaches, and ephemeral winds scour the mind. What happens if one’s mind is caught in a beacon when it fails, no one knows.

Free Your Mind [Self]

On a mountainous continent toward the Hub exists a machine, buried deep below the earth. Its tendrils stretch throughout the land: veins of gold carrying carefully patterned pulses, in a cadence that resonates with the human mind. After a few days of exposure, the resonance reaches a peak and any mind-control effects are broken. The long-missing creators of this device would likely appreciate that their device is no longer necessary with the advent of the Gift. Nevertheless, the tendrils continue to slowly grow, stretching beyond the continent and beneath the sea.

The Ghost-Mind [Research]

Ghost-binding was once considered a valued art among the world’s necromancers. One nation’s magi bound a seething mass of ghosts in a web across their continent, calling them simultaneously to multiple summoning circles. They were stretched thin, able to hear what was said in one place and repeat it in another. They quivvered in response to death-flow and life-flow. Their mind was amalgamated, so they thought as one. So say the records. Once the souls of these ghosts moved to their next lives, the ghosts themselves became just tattered memories, whispering incoherently in the many circles to which they are still bound.

The Hedge [Tradecraft]

A long-dead nation wished to spy on its enemy, so their Earthpower adepts build a means to conceal people as they traveled. A quick-growing plant insinuated itself across thousands of miles, hiding near trees and in ravines. Those with a certain tattoo could enter and leave, and see out from within. Then those enemies turned the hedge around on itself, and everyone who entered was lost forever.

Jet Streams [Industry]

The upper atmosphere of the Basin is generally calm and unperturbed. One ancient culture thought it would be more useful if there were grand currents there, as there are in the seas. Presumably they would have used them to propel airships more quickly. Now there are only a few of these blisteringly fast corridors left. They wreak havoc on the weather patterns at their beginning and end, disrupting the flow and causing freak occurences like triangular hurricanes or standing lightning.

Potion-fruit Forest [Industry]

Potion-fruit trees are a standard trick for the Hearth-kin, a way to have nature work certain rituals for them as they take on other tasks. Long ago, someone seeded multiple continents with such trees. In the intervening milennia, those trees have hybridized with local flora. Some of the resulting plants bear delicious-tasting or delicately scented potions. Most, however, have gone awry, and bear fruits that are poisonous, acidic, cursed, or downright explosive.

Lost Expressions

The spells of many Traditions are lost forever in the Basin’s billions of years of history. Those most easily recovered are from the Paths of Language or Geometry, simply because their recordings are more durable, but most Founts and Paths have ways of preserving records for the distant future.

Most of the Expressions listed here are merely fragments of existing arts. Adding them to one’s repertoire would not require using up a Core Expression slot, assuming one already knew the related art.

Acceleration, an expression of Industry that grants greater and greater speed. Found in geometrical diagrams traced into the wheels of an indestructible metallic wagon in a crater on a mountainside.
Accept the Offering, which purports to receive a soul from the Uncountable Spinners if one has a mystic connection to it. Found in a pattern of beads on a temple curtain.
Aggravation, which makes the caster so distracted and upset that they cannot focus well enough to act on certain expressions of Trickery. Pieced together from a broken tablet with a boot print upon it.
Air-gills, a spell designed for aquatic beings. Traded to the Archive by a traveler from another world.
All The Way To The End Of Time, a dreamshaping expression that takes existing structures or landscape featuers and replicates them infinitely. Found in a Dream Realm composed of endless staircases.
Become the Heart, which shapeshifts you in to an immaterial manifestation of warm feeling of home. Discovered by rescuing its creator from the spell itself.
Beneath the Depths, a flawed art for underwater adaptation, discovered on the corpse of an deep-sea explorer
Beyond the Grasp of Years, which coats an object in amber to preserve it for the future. Discovered in the patterns of buzzing from giant bees.
Bone Dagger, a Weaponry expression, reverse-engineered from a cache of examples.
Bridge of Escape, an attempt to access the Travel lattice but without being able to specify the destination. Found on a clay tablet falling through the Travel Lattice.
Bury the Evidence, which interrs prepared materials within the earth. Found inscribed on a cask deep within the Basin’s crust.
Busy Household, an illusion that makes it appear as if a house had multiple people inside and lights on. Found by the Unroyal in a distant land and turned over to the Archive.
Call the Dream, which overlays a Dream Realm onto the physical world. Found in a set of fallacious equations.
Call the Ghostly Iron, an Energy Wave variant that only works in regions with buried parallel lines of steel deposits. Found inscribed on a more-preserved stretch of those deposits.
Call to Aid, which sends up a flare visible and audible for many koss. Developed and lost by many a civilization long before the Gift.
Chime of Attention, which urges all those nearby to look at the caster or else directly away from them. Found in a bell-maker’s journal.
Chorus of Joy, which inspires those who hear it to have good cheer and attempt great deeds. Pieced together from a hundred hymnals.
Clear the Lens, a now-useless spell to improve a long-lost scrying technique. Found in the strange curvatures on a telescope lens.
Comprehend the Ailing Body, which diagnoses the root cause of physical illnesses. Found in the ruins of a hospital.
Consummate Understanding, which lets you come away from Rapport with temporary but complete understanding of what your Rapport partners knew. Found hidden in a calendrical scroll of love poems.
Conviction, which increases one’s resistance to persuasion by amplifying stubbornness. Heard in songs passed down from a long-dead culture.
Count the Stars, a set of mathematical techniques for Mental Acuity. Found by reading the patterns left on a three-dimensional abacus.
Crimson Massacre, a variant on Stutter-stepping that dips into the Red Space. Causes severely depleted flow, and thus doesn’t last very long. Found on the sash of a corpse in the Red Space.
Crown of Fire, a Terror expression that’s less “horror” and more “awe”. Discovered in a palace when the Worldbuilders called a city forward in time.
Cut the Circle, which strikes against magical patterns and diagrams in an attempt to disrupt spells on the path of Geometry. (Works as per normal conflict rules.) Found in Geometer territory and immediately confiscated by the Guild.
Damn the Path, a ritual which creates a curse that jumps from one user of a particular Tradition to another, burning out particular Expressions. Found at the apparent site of an interrupted ritual.
Darts of Ice, an Energy Wave variant, discovered in a desert crypt
Devil’s Voice, a now-useless art of secution. Traded for a fragment of soul in a demon market.
Die, an instant-death curse. People in the modern age are well-defended against such things. The counter-curse is recorded in a historical text; the original was reverse-engineered from it.
Divide the Foe, which harmlessly splits an armed force into two smaller units. Found in scrimshaw on half of a skeleton.
Draw and Bind, a major ritual that opens a permanent portal to elsewhere in the Kaleidoscope. Found as a half-finished mosaic.
Draw the Flame Within, a Knotwork precursor that allows one to breathe in flames and thus store fire-flow. Deduced from the reagents in a long-lost storeroom.
Everlasting Youth, a spell of beauty and cosmetology, inscribed on the back of a mirror
Extended Grasp, a variant of Telekinesis that gives less strength but full sense of touch. Reverse-engineered from a wand that casts the spell.
Extract Mortality, which turns its victim into a unique type of flow parasite. Found being traded in a soul market in the Worlds Beyond.
Faces of Horror, which intentionally clones artwork to disturbing effect (though not in game terms). Reverse-engineered from a Realm Beyond filled with such paintings.
Final Revenge, which turns the caster into a mindless beast of creeping fungus and deadly spores. Brought back in time by a Worldbuilder citizen.
Flow-repelling Shell, a failed attempt to create local Null Zones. Found in an impossibly old hut within a wild magic zone.
Focus the Lance of Oblivion, a now-useless spell that activates a long-destroyed magical superweapon. Found in the capitol of an overthrown ancient empire.
Fox of the Founts, which substitutes another Fount for your own at the cost of 1 Reserve. Found in a maelstrom of flow where it plunges underground.
Ghost Stories, a Psychometry technique that works best on murder scenes. Appears on the foreheads of thrice-killed ghosts on a forever-shadowed island.
Globular Phantasms, which its creator originally mistook for a mirage-inducing drug-like art, but which actually views the microscopic world. Found in with a large collection of drug magics.
Grant of Vitality, which enchants any living being with regenerative powers. Found in a half-sunken city from a bygone era.
Hammer-And-Anvil Hands, a Distillation expression. Part of an Arete manual found undamaged in an ancient forge.
Hear the Silence, a Sixth Sense variant that detects flow parasites at a distance. Found in a strongbox on a panaquin carried eternally by mindless wraiths.
Hear the World Spirits, a variant of Expanded Expertise that grants one specific type of Archetypal. Attested to in ancient tablets and recovered from the very spirits who first taught it.
Horn of Purity, a Healing expression that flushes poison from the system. Found in situ on the horns of many creatures near the Hub.
Hub and Home, a direction-finding spell that predates the Travel Lattice. Reverse-engineered from a Hub-seeking compass.
Infinite Viewpoints, a Curse/Hallucination hybrid. Found in patterns left by ley lines in a destroyed city.
Inner Purification, which uses trace aspects from inside one’s own body to purify swallowed material into suitable reagents. Found in the introductory tomes of a Blood Magic / Alchemy Tradition.
Joining of Minds, which creates an inextricable two-person group mind. Found as a holy rite in a long-lost temple to duality.
Know the Wild, which lets one hear whispers from nature spirits and survive the wilderness more effectively. Learned from a spirit of a swamp after a long slumber.
Labor No More, a minor ritual that creates a more capable mystic servitors that does the work with which you’re most familiar. Found incribed on a half-dozen run-down automata in a Dream Realm.
Leave the Ground, in which one leaps to space. Found inscribed on the 400 prayer beads of a rosary.
Lift the Sunken Lands, a Great-Work-level Ritual that draws continents up from beneath the ocean. Found on the highest mountaintop in the Guild’s homelands.
Locked into Thought, a curse that mentally traps one’s opponent in a game that they must win to escape. (Resisted with Mystery rather than Self.) Discovered in the positions of the far-separated pieces on a game board that spanned nations.
Make Way, which deconjures stone, dirt, and other examples of elemental earth. Found in a cave in the Sovereigns’ territory.
Meteor Self, which turns the caster into a dense purple metal that can survive a fall from any height. Found inscribed on one of the Ten-Crore Stones.
Mirror World Continuance, a variant of immortality that allows one to live within a mirror and move to nearby ones. Taught by someone still alive inside of one of them.
No More Pigeons, a Warding variant that kept a warlock’s palace cleaner. Found inscribed on that very same palace.
No You, which uses a crude form of the Shell Game to reverse mind control spells. Found written in cyphered form in a sorceror’s timeworn notebook.
Open the Third Eye, an Enchantment expression that grants Second Sight. Found in Nova territory in a library that was previously thought picked clean.
Paean to Mayhem, used solely to generate Chaotic Flow side-effects. Discovered in the form of aspects preserved in a block of frozen time.
Perfect Silence, an expression of the Self for calm and meditation. Found in the ringing of a long-lost bell.
Plow, which plows fields, heard forever echoing from the mountains in a verdant valley
Primordial Call, which brings up creatures of the sea to help one travel the oceans. Water-breathing not included. Discovered in the songs of cetaceans.
Puppet’s Poles, a mind-control spell (now useless), discovered in the ruins of a Fraternity of Truth headquarters
Rain of Silver, a hail-like Weatherwork expression. Found in a scroll, locked in a case, locked in a ches, locked in a vault, encased in a block of solid quartz.
Reach Toward Divinity, a state-approved version of Becoming from a long-dead religion, found written in sapphire in a hell.
Remember Love, which allows one to relive moments of love and care. Found in one of Diadem’s vassal states where its practice had nearly been forgotten.
Rite of Cleansing, a ritual to re-aspect flow over a large area using the shared beliefs of those who live there. Reconstructed from twenty fragments found in a Null Zone.
Sacred Form, which shapeshifts the caster into a swan (which was holy to the culture that made the spell). Found on a stone relief in a city’s center.
Seek Magi, a once-useful spell that allowed one to feel changes in the flow from a great distance. Found inscribed in the floor of a temple.
Shared Souls, in which four consenting magi each end up with a quarter of each others’ souls, mixing their magic signatures. Found in three different spellbooks from the distant past.
Speak to the Square, which allows you to speak so that anyone in one specific ruined city square can hear you - from anywhere. Found in an ancient wizard’s pocket dimension before it collapsed.
Spider Feels the Web, a ritual which gives the caster a mystic connection to every house in a settlement, letting them use certain magics (like Farspeech) on those who live there.
Split the Sky, a defense against attacks from above. Found forced into the ground near a Ten-Crore Stones strike site.
Stolen Face, which makes you look like someone else (in more than just your literal face). Found hidden in the memoirs of a famous thief from a thousand years ago.
Strength of the Serpent, a blood magic spell that bestows power based on what animal’s blood you absorb. Found in the pattern of scales on an extinct snake.
Suspended Life, which kills the caster and resurrects them one day later. Found on a tablet in the previous homelands of Those Above.
Take the Burden of the Wounded, an Arete expression wherein the caster heals another by absorbing their wounds. Much faster than traditional Healing arts, though with an obvious drawback. Taught by instructors in a World Beyond that revolves around wisdom and sacrifice.
The Climbing Seed, an example of Nature-work that only sprouts on solid stone and overgrows stone buildings. Observed in situ.
The Fan of Journeys, not an object but a spell which whisks ships into the sky to sail there. Found abandoned in the Aliala, the Dream of Flying.
The Forty-Four Assembled, which calls a specific variant of mystic defender. Found on the statues of those bygone warriors.
The Right Play, apparently used by one wizard to cheat on others at cards. Found near the murder site.
The Strategist’s Dream, a Hypnopraxis technique that permits the caster to replay battles or plan for future ones. Found inscribed on a sword preserved within a massive shard of amber.
The Thousand Ton Curse, which leaves its victims unable to move under the weight. Found in mid-air, five koss up.
The Tired-Eyes Curse, which is actually an art of the Shroud. Found already mixed and ready for use in an ancient cauldron.
Tide Knows Tide, which turns movements of the flow directly into mechanical motion (so as to create wind or speed travel). Written into a pattern of islands and read from their map.
To The Horizon, yet another broken teleportation method. Found on a body in deep space.
Track the Soul, which allows you to track down someone if you have a piece of their soul. Found inscribed on the soul of a dragon that sleeps for a million years.
Unfailing Wellspring, an apparently inaccurately-named spell that calls up flow where there is none. Found in a wizard’s decrepit tower in a deep Null Zone.
Unstable Duplication, which makes copies that may or may not make copies of themselves. Found on a scroll next to a skeleton crushed beneath thousands of identical books.
War’s End, a method for disconnection. Assembled from shards of ceramic disks scattered across a continent.
Waste of Time, a fish-summoning spell apparently not thought worth passing on by a magus who nevertheless recorded it for posterity in the Universal Repositories.
Water to Gold, because who keeps stacks of lead lying around, honestly? Found next to an extremely convincing statue of a human being.
Wave Crashes Last, which delays certain Energy Wave variants until they are released by the caster. Found in a silver-and-black book left near an ancient dueling circle.
Winged Messenger, which sends a conjured bird to deliver a message to someone. Found on the sacred wrappings of a mummy, beneath a step pyramid covered in bird skeletons.
Wings of Light, a spell of flight that is stronger during the day. Found in a prayer book.
Witness the Balance, an Infrastructure-level art that reveals the “balance” of a city according to a long-lost culture’s ideas of balance. Carved into the ceiling of a collapsed underground tunnel.

When is it a new Expression?

When it does something different, or shifts to a new Nature.

Mystical Infrastructure

List by Nature

Industry: Dream Factories, Flow Dynamics, the Gracious Attendants in Miniature, Raise from the Strata
Research: Generative Zones, Gyre-Fusing Mosaics
Self: Bridge to the Past, the Forge of Sleep, the Resonance of Control
Statecraft: Butterflies of Peace, Rightthink Plagues
Tradecraft: All Roads, the Mists of Concealment
War: Seismic Mastery, the Threefold Gates of Retribution

Infrastructure-Scale Expressions

All Roads Lead To...

Nature: Tradecraft
Common Founts: Glory, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Minimal across the area affected
Common side-effects: Warped flow

Nations using this Expression bend the feet of wanderers toward a specific location, typically a capitol or heavily fortified city. Locals can get around without (much) trouble, but visitors and spies end up turned around, detoured, distracted, and wondering how they took a wrong turn. The spell leaks into the Travel lattice, rerouting bridges and shifting lattice points when people aren’t looking.

This spell can’t simply turn visitors away, but see The Mists of Concealment below for that.

Some Paths lay down the road-bed in mystic designs or inscribe runes with the road network itself. Others stoke the fire for the bricks with pieces of homes, to draw people to the nation’s heart. Glimmermere simply makes the destination more beautiful and draws the eye.

Bridge to the Past

Nature: Self
Common Founts: Necromancy
Flow needs: Large at the moment of activation
Common side-effects: Chakra Occlusion

This is the art by which the Worldmakers bring their willing descendants back from the future to aid them in the present. It requires much in the way of stable construction, redirected ley lines, and flow aspected to feelings of belonging, nostalgia, or deja vu.

This art has a variety of odd side-effects, including the travelers having odd gaps in their memories (actually a result of branching timelines) and the failure of the True Speech (words for concepts that haven’t been invented yet). Even the Worldbuilders’ Traditions are oddly named because they came from the future - better versions of their previous Traditions that have since replaced the forgotten originals.

The particular variety of Infrastructure-level chakra occlusion created by this art is to foil attempts at Precognition within the city or nation that employs it. The more people from the future who are present, the more impossible the art becomes. The Worldbuilders have outlawed research into any reverse version of the spell for fear of what it would do to the highly valued art of Psychometry. Naturally, Nova is working on it.

Butterflies of Peace

Nature: Statecraft
Common Founts: Earthpower, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Large where the effect is created
Common side-effects: Emotional fatigue, Warped flow

Sometimes a bit of beauty is all it takes for people to relax. The heart comes to rest, peace is easier to feel, and all seems right with the world.

City-states who deploy the Butterflies of Peace grow special gardens to feed them (whether real or in dream), and let them fly with a little wind to guide them. Sometimes they’re sent on a journey of a thousand miles; other times just to the neighboring city or even to certain local neighborhoods. Wherever they go, they spread calm and contentment.

Note that the Butterflies of Peace are not an expression of the War-nature. They can help establish a truce or treaty, but will not make an ambush easier or allow armies to invade a lulled population. For warlike uses, deploy the Cicadas of False Security, or the Locusts of Despite, whose effects and forms are easily distinguished from one another. Not that a tool that generates contentment is entirely without potential sinister uses, but those they can achieve fall under Statecraft.

Dream Factories

Nature: Industry
Common Founts: Alchemy, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Tremendous on the day the factory is moved, Minimal to affected dreamers afterward
Common side-effects: Warped flow, Emotional fatigue

The factories required for large-scale magitech industry are large, flow-hungry, and often ugly. This art pushes them into the Dream Realms. There, they draw on expansive supplies of well-aspected flow and don’t need to worry about polluted flow causing issues in nearby city-states. The products can be extracted back to the physical world and the factory stays out of anyone’s backyard.

Of course, the side effects don’t simply go away. Their effects on actual dreamers in the nation (or nearby) can be striking. A factory sensibly housed in a Dream Realm related to feelings of productivity may end up making workers in the Basin feel sluggish when they wake in the morning, and they may dread going to sleep at night without realizing why. A citizenry trained in oneiromantic techniques will eventually figure out what’s going on, but a less dream-savvy populace may struggle for months or years before the truth comes out.

For factories that create Dream Realms, see the Forge of Sleep below.

Flow Dynamics

Nature: Industry
Common Founts: All, see below
Flow needs: A small fraction of the diverted or adjusted flow
Common side-effects: Chaotic flow, Warped flow

Nearly every civilization adjusts the local flow to some extent. Nova Commonwealth refers to this class of techniques as “flow dynamics”, and the term has caught on with the Geometers and Those Above. Examples of such techniques include:

Funneling & channeling flow via wards (Alchemy, Earthpower)
Fracturing or merging ley lines in gigantic prisms (Elementalism, Glory)
Municipal Knots that keeps flow moving in a loop through the city, pulling it in from outside (Arete, Alchemy)
Filtering aspects to permit certain things and remove others (Necromancy, Elementalism)
Aspect generators, like meditation centers for calm flow, ever-burning flames for inspiration-aspected flow (or simply fire-flow), or gratitude centers placed upstream from hospitals to generate benevolent flow (Arete, Glory, Necromancy)

The more changes that are required to the local flow, the worse the side effects will be. The Worldbuilders, with their hunger for territory of any kind regardless of its suitability, run into these issues often.

the Forge of Sleep

Nature: Self
Common Founts: Glory, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Minimal across a large area, until the realm stabilizes
Common side-effects: Chaotic flow

Someone with the art of Dreamshaping can create new dreams. Groups capable of using the Forge of Sleep can create new Dream Realms. These are not the tiny Dream Realms created by individual dreamers, linked tenuously to existing concepts and emotions. These are vast, custom-built existences capable of supporting untold numbers of sentient beings.

New Dream Realms are particularly tricky to create because there are so many already in existence, each tied to a particular thought, emotion, or whimsy. The Forge requires coming up with a genuinely new thought, or at least one so rare that the previous Dream Realm is weak and can be overwritten with the new one.

The character of the realm will be shaped by the idea itself, but the metaphysics technicians who deploy the rituals and techniques of sleep-forging have a great deal of latitude within that space. For instance, a world created from the feeling of joy at seeing a whale breaching will necessarily have water and whales - but whether it has islands, boats, sunshine, rainbows, or nothing but ocean surface as far as the eye can see is up for the theurges to decide.

Generative Zones

Nature: Research
Common Founts: Elementalism, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Varies widely, spread across about a city block
Common side-effects: Chaotic flow

There is a joke among scholars that a Generative Zone is effectively just a wild magic zone and someone with a pad of paper.

Generative Zones are created by feeding diverse flows into a small area, with a variety of different objects and materials inside, and changing up the combination on an irregular basis. Eventually some interesting combination of flows and placements will be achieved, and a magical effect will manifest. Smaller flows will engender subtle effects; larger ones lead to more dramatic manifestations (though not necessarily more useful ones). From there it’s a matter of figuring out how to replicate the effect, and hoping that it’s actually novel.

The mental and emotional states of the researchers are, of course, of paramount importance in engendering the effect. Sometimes a degree of objectivity in the observer is helpful, but it’s important to test different levels of attachment to the outcome, irritation, boredom, positivity, etc. Second-degree observers are often employed, who watch from a greater remove so as to interfere less with the local emotional resonance, but the knowledge that they are being observed also changes the local observer’s view of the situation.

Most groups that follow the path of wild magic employ Generative Zones in their magical research.

the Gracious Attendants in Miniature

Nature: Industry
Common Founts: Alchemy, Necromancy
Flow needs: Small over the area the spirits are active
Common side-effects: Flow depletion

The Gracious Attendants in Miniature are a veritable flood of tiny automata, all enchanted to obey the commands of those nearby. They are created by setting a group of Minuscule Servitors about the task of creating automata, and then taking care to provide those automata with the flow they need.

Gracious Attendants are somewhat specialized, with only a few specific tasks they can accomplish. Those created in the Guild can conjure from the Consensus Canon or perform Weather-Working to make the weather more mild. Those in the Cult, collected and accreted from lost scraps of ancient ghosts, can carry messages using Farspeech with one another. They also have the unfortunate tendency to spirit-walk out of their containment. The gods of the Ægis seek to create a variety that heals all who are within, and Guises outsiders so that they may fit in regardless of their strangeness.

All of these functions are completed without the commanding wizard (or even the rare non-wizard!) needing to tap any flow. Only knowledge of the access method is required.

Gyre-Fusing Mosaics

Nature: Research
Common Founts: Alchemy, Arete, Glory
Flow needs: Large in a small area
Common side-effects: Emotional fatigue

Careful scrutiny of ley lines and ambient flow can tell you what’s happening upstream of your location. Gyre-Fusing Mosaics are designed to perform some very careful scrutiny indeed, picking apart individual eddies of the flow to turn tiny scraps of evidence into a larger picture.

Gyre-Fusing Mosaics were developed in the Geometer’s Guild as shifting tile mosaics of lines and curves. Other civilizations implement the same approach in other ways: as ever-weaving tapestries, giant mandalas of drifting sand, tubes of bubbling and color-changing reagents, even the light on the floor from carefully-arranged stained glass.

Regardless of physical form, these techniques provide magical scholars with a minute-by-minute readout of what natures are being expressed upstream, and to what degree. They can’t pick out individual spells, but they can find powerful magical creatures, watch energetic events like thunderstorms for complex phenomena, and feel ley lines splitting or merging tens of thousands of miles downstream. They’re part telescope, part spectrometer, part seismograph, and about the size and weight of a pipe organ.

It’s only a matter of time before this technique moves from Research into Tradecraft. The potential to detect an opponent’s mass use of Travel or deployment of the Ten-Crore Stones is too valuable to pass up.

the Mists of Concealment

Nature: Tradecraft
Common Founts: Earthpower, Elementalism, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Small over the affected area
Common side-effects: Warped flow

The “All roads lead to…” art above directs visitors to a specific location. The Mists of Concealment make it impossible to find a particular place at all. Those who live inside the effect can find their way back in if they retain a connection to their homeland (see Getting Lost, Sorc page 183). Those outside will contend with the Mists every time they attempt to enter.

The Mists of Concealment make their lands a somewhat uncomfortable place to live. The sky is rarely visible, and only at night.

Raise from the Strata

Nature: Industry
Common Founts: Necromancy
Flow needs: Tremendous over about a city block
Common side-effects: Flow depletion, Warped flow

It is by this art that the Worldbuilders pull structures from the distant past into the present. Enough detail is given in their writeup in Sorc (page 201) that we need say little here. The ritual is lengthy - it takes weeks or months to dredge a new city into the present one block at a time - but it’s still much faster than building it.

More than one Nova sect is fascinated by this art, as it reaches much farther back than Psychometry can, and with less skill required. They attempt to adjust it into the Research-Nature, which would allow them to sense a greater variety of structures, objects, and perhaps even people in the distant past.

the Resonance of Control

Nature: Self
Common Founts: Glory, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Minimal over the affected area
Common side-effects: Warped flow, Emotional burn-in

Far from being a tool for controling a population, the Resonance of Control is a means for the population to control itself. It adjusts the flow of a large region - in the case of the Golden Ægis, their entire civilization - to help people control their own emotions and stay level-headed in the face of danger. The effect is subtle. Individuals may still panic, but on the whole, groups panic less, and people do what they were taught instead of what their instincts say.

Groups that know this art may spend Reserve to de-escalate large-scale conflicts even if they don’t have an appropriate Core Value. This applies only to groups large enough to qualify for Infrastructure - individuals still need an appropriate CV to de-escalate.

Rightthink Plagues

Nature: Statecraft
Common Founts: Glory, Oneiromancy
Flow needs: Minimal over the affected area
Common side-effects: Emotional burn-in

Diadem developed this art in an attempt to remove the Unroyal from their territory. Rightthink Plagues make it more difficult to remember certain emotions, ideas, and patterns of speech. They thus block certain Dream Realms out from a population, making it impossible to use them as transit or escape where those people live.

Rightthink Plagues are effectively a low-grade Curse That Creeps (see Curses in Sorc, page 121). They have the Silent descriptor, so one must look for them specifically. If counteracted, the effects generally recede. However, if the Plague has been in effect for several years, it is likely to have permanently changed its victims’ habits, and removal of the magical effect will do nothing.

Rightthink Plagues are most effective in places where the population has been informed that they are being deployed and agrees to it. This is the case for most of the nobility and some of the underclass in Diadem. The Ægis is considering deploying Rightthink Plagues in its own population. It has not told the Unroyal about this yet.

Seismic Mastery

Nature: War
Common Founts: Earthpower, Elementalism
Flow needs: Tremendous in the control center
Common side-effects: Flow depletion, Warped flow

When a civilization has a large number of city-states on the same continent, they open lines of power and opportunity that were not available before. This large-scale War expression drives the flow of rage, fire, or passion deep into the Basin’s crust, where it generates earthquakes and spawns new volcanoes. An undefended city would be reduced to smouldering rubble in hours.

Seismic Mastery is one example of large-scale thaumaturgical weaponry. Other techniques, such as Weather Mastery, Sea Mastery, etc. could also be created along the same lines.

the Threefold Gates of Retribution

Nature: War
Common Founts: All
Flow needs: Large in the places the
Common side-effects: Chaotic flow

Briefly mentioned in Sorcerously Advanced (page 124, alongside Enegy Waves), the Threefold Gates of Retribution are a defensive system that lashes out when a city is attacked. They are a set of standing stones, arcane symbols, ever-ringing bells, or other longstanding magical structures, which must be placed outside of the area they protect (traditionally in sets of three). As known weak points in a city-state’s defense, they are invariably well-defended.

The Threefold Gates use the Conflict rules like most any other interaction, but that on its own is usually enough to leave a solo attacker burned from the inside out by their own power. The Threefold Gates are also an important part of Infrastructure-level defenses, helping to deflect such measures as Seismic Mastery.

Living With Magic

This chapter contains essays about what it's like to live with magic in the Basin, how people deal with it on a day-to-day basis, and what Natures really "mean".

Like the Advice chapter in Sorc, this chapter is written from the perspective of me, the game designer, talking directly with you, the reader.

What "Nature" Is

Sometimes in Sorc I refer to Nature scores by their numerical value for convenience, but the best phrase I've found is really "deep in the X-Nature." Nature is built via inclination and training, but neither of those things are what it really represents. Nature is about connection with fundamental aspects of being sentient.

You have Nature because that's who you are.

More accurately, you have potential Nature because of who you are. Properly expressing your Nature requires tools and training. Spells are those tools, which is why spells are often referred to as Expressions. Someone who is very combative and aggressive but knows no actual spells of War will have a very low effective War score, and would get trounced by someone with a better ability to express their Nature. For ease of game play we don't track potential Nature scores - we only track effective scores, the ones that determine what you can actually use. I'll talk more about this below.

When one person has two different Traditions, their Nature scores can vary for two reasons. First, they might not always have the skills necessary to express all that they are. Second, Traditions represent not only metaphysical paths and sources of power, but also mindsets and habits of thought. Some people, when they change Traditions, take on such a different mentality that their Nature scores must change to represent that. For example, ghosts from the Cult use The Practice for their day-to-day life or work, and The Rage when they need (or want) to fight. Nearly all Cultists have a higher War-Nature in when they're in The Rage. That's what The Rage is for. It not only has more tools to express the War-nature, people instinctively swap into it it when they know they're going to have to fight for their lives, or when they're expressing deep emotional pain.

Separating the Game Attributes

If you're having trouble figuring out exactly what's supposed to go into Natures, Core Values, and Professions, and why I'm saying that skill is part of Nature when it clearly belongs in a Profession, these concepts are intentionally not well-separated in this game. If you want a set of game attributes that doesn't overlap, here are two options:

Remove Natures and play just with CVs and Professions. Use Professions to gate Expressions - keep the same minimum requirement but let the player choose appropriate Professions that are required instead of Nature. Make the Conflict total into CV x Profession, with any bonuses adding to Profession.
Do the reverse: remove CVs and Professions and use just Natures in the game. Make the Conflict total into Nature x Same Nature. Some conflicts might better be represented by Nature x Different Nature, but that's up to you. Any bonuses are added to one of the Nature scores (not both).

What Nature Says

As mentioned in Sorc (page 104), children are born without magic. Their effective Nature scores are 1. Where they go from there depends on how they grow up and who they become.

Nature 1

In an adult, scores of 1 most often indicate a lack of interest in that particular area. Someone who doesn't have a deceptive bone in their body will have Trickery 1. Someone who wouldn't hurt a fly would have War 1.

Their disinterest also means they won't train in that area. Their lack of skill means that their effective Nature will be low even if they suddenly wish it weren't. Scores of 1 can be a result of not receiving any experience or training in a particular area. It's possible for a very productive person who enjoys making things with their hands to have Industry 1, but it's very unlikely. In our world, the equivalent would be someone who says they love crafting but have never learned to knit, never practiced whittling, doesn't garden, doesn't cook, and in short have evaded almost every opportunity to learn and practice the arts of Industry.

People raised in Null Zones always have an effective score of 1 in their Natures. While it might make sense for e.g. a very compassionate person to have Communion 2 or higher, a lack of flow makes it impossible for them to access the benefits of their true selves. Returners raised outside a null zone, where flow is broadly available, actually do have Natures limited to 1. They're been raised to avoid strong emotions. As you can guess, this kind of mental conditioning doesn't always work.

Nature 2-4

Growing children, adolescents, and young adults raise their Natures by following their interests and learning more about them. Most adults will have Nature scores between 2 and 4.

People with Nature 2 or 4 are what you might think of as "normally interested" in a particular area. You might say, "If want to learn some shapechanging tricks, talk to Ley-Star-Wealth. They're really into it." Or, "Sprint of Seventh Ward? Yeah, she never really liked geometry, can't conjure a sturdy house to save her life." They're within the typical expected range of interests and abilities in the Basin.

Nature 3 is a fairly common baseline across the Basin. Certain Natures can be lower in certain civilizations. War, especially, is lower across more peaceful regions. Other Natures tend to be day-to-day requirements for life and society. Nature 3 has a number of very enticing benefits: Universal Repositories, improved Immortality, Travel, reading people more effectively, pranking people with the Shell Game... These things are a big deal, especially when your peer group has them and you don't. They're marks of adulthood.

Nature 5

Nature 5 requires a lot of interest and a lot of effort, with the former typically leading to the latter. Nature 5 isn't truly rare - you'll find quite a few people with Nature 5 in any given city - but this level comes from a substantial focus.

Nature 5 doesn't have a lot of new techniques as compared with Nature 4, at least in the game as written so far. However, it's still twice as fast in Rituals, more potent, and opens up a few odd tricks that people won't expect and don't always plan for. Even in a world where everyone's a magician, Nature 5 is a step above. As the average magical prowess of the Basin increases (see The Advance Of Magic below), these will become game-changers in the lives of people across the world.

Maintaining Natures

Maintaining Nature 1 or 2 takes nothing.

Maintaining Nature 3 takes some work, but not a lot. Leisure time is fairly commonly available across the Basin, so most people find a few hours a week to "work out", as it were.

Maintaining Nature 4 and 5 takes more work, so they're generally connected to someone's role in society. Profession and Nature are mutually reinforcing in this world. A healer finds it much easier to maintain Communion 5 because it's the muscle they use day in and day out. A scholar's high Mystery score is kept sharp by the translation work they do.

The Advance Of Magic

The average magical prowess of Basin natives is increasing with time.

When the Gift was given, everyone had an effective Nature cap of 3. Many spells were unknown, or known only to a handful of magi like the Fellowship of Truth or the Geometer's Guild. Most people didn't know efficient processes by which to attain a deeper connection with their Natures. Even if someone managed to attain a Nature of 4 or 5, they had no tools with which to express it. Their effective Nature was still 3. Even the Fellowship and the Geometers were capped at 3 at that time. The Gift opened up a greater potential in them, but they couldn't take advantage of it. Many people were stuck at 2 until they stole, rediscovered, or invented new Expressions.

Over time, as magical research and archaeology expanded the tools available, Nature 4 and 5 became accessible. People also learned effective ways to reach higher Nature scores faster. This process of growth hasn't stopped. Some time in the not-too-distant future, Nature 6 will be just as accessible as Nature 5 is now. The exact timeline for this is left up to the GM, but it's unlikely to be a smooth and uniform transition. Some Natures will no doubt come earlier by coincidence or necessity.

Will there be Nature 7 eventually? Yes. Nature 8, 9, 10? Yes. Some day, Nature 5 will be what people achieve when they're not very interested in what they're doing. It's going to be a hell of a time.

If you want to play this process out, go for it. You might have a game that skips centuries, or one where all of this happens in a rapidly accelerating singularity scenario. (I recommend allowing higher Profession levels as well, since using a Profession involves magic for nearly everyone.)

Changing Traditions

What's the process for changing Traditions? What does your character actually do, and why does it cost Reserve?

In game terms, a Tradition is a Path, a Fount, and a set of Core Expressions. In the world of the game, a Tradition encompasses much more. It's a way of thinking, a set of tools, and an approach to life. It's a connection to a universal emanation of power. Traditions are enmeshed with culture and mindset.

To switch Traditions, a magus puts down the tools of their old trade and takes up new ones. In simpler cases they put away dusts and powders and ready a compass and stylus, or perhaps clear their voice and take a deep breath to sing. Other magi have greater challenges. Those who walk the path of Belief must put those beliefs down. Those with Patrons must beseech and appease them. Even two Traditions that share a Path will have differences in interpretation and intent. As anyone who has learned multiple languages or martial arts styles knows, sometimes the closest pairings are the hardest to keep separate.

Changing Traditions costs Reserve because all of that takes effort and creates waste. Blood magic requires an initial investment. Wild magic disrupts other effects. Careful procedures can mitigate these issues, but the very mindset of caution is not conducive to some forms of magic! In the end, only extensive practice makes the transition smooth - or as smooth as possible.

The Twist effects of changing Traditions come purely from metagame concerns. There's no in-world effect, so there's no in-world justification needed.

Everyday Magic

If you walk down a stereotypical street in any given civilization, what does it look like? What's happening that might be surprising to someone who isn't used to it? The corebook already covers some of this, so I'll skip details that have already been discussed.

the Cult: Most people are a bit see-through. You'll still see children (who are also ghosts) and pets (sometimes ghosts, but not always) running and playing. Solid-looking people are less likely to be mortals and more likely to be different kinds of ghosts from other civilizations. People talk "to themselves" frequently - they're actually communing with their ancestors. Strange, baroque expressions of speech are common, as the True Speech translates linguistic magic into comprehensible words. If there's a problem brewing, everyone's going to know about it as the manifestations of the Rage rise: deep sounds, green flame, and the ground shaking angrily.
Diadem: Class is everything in Diadem. A few examples: A fair number of people in Diadem have mixed the intangible with their physical forms. The upperclass, with the tradition of Transubstantiation, hybridize with thought and emotion. The underclass, with Drudgery, become part elemental. The upperclass wears face paint and body rouge infused with magical reagents. Some of the underclass come from cultures that wear face paint, but they don't do it here because of the social implications. The underclass read and debate and exercise for the Path of Discipline, often in public. The upperclass buy their reagents and practice mixing them away from judgmental eyes. Upperclass homes are spiraling shells and horns; underclass homes are solid stone blocks. The upperclass comes to underclass areas seeking entertainment, labor, or exotic things from far-away lands. The underclass visit upperclass areas as little as possible - generally only when they are employed for a specific purpose.
the Geometers: Unlike in many civilizations, much of the actual magic of the Guild is invisible. The causes are clear - lines, arcs, etc. - but the effects are often internal, hidden, or purely mental. It's the knock-on effects of magic, the second-order effects, that are visible. Mutitasking rituals in the Guild create automata, so a fair number of automata walk the streets and stand in key locations, helping with any tasks simple enough for their programming. Using Travel requires reaching a nexus, where thousands of nodes have been pulled together, so many people adopt faster modes of local transportation, like flight or space-warping tricks for running. Satori is a common enhanced experience in the Guild, so most infrastructure is either brilliantly engineered or a mess of competing priorities.
Glimmermere: Expect the fantastic, the fanciful, and the phantasmagorical. A spiral staircase goes nowhere, but the door at the top opens to a secret, hidden house. Swaths of colors across the sky match the mood, dark and ominous where grave matters are discussed, bright and comforting where children are raised. Here, any form of art is likely a form of magic, and everything is a suitable canvas. Even the grass might be groomed into a vast carpet of beauty that shifts the clouds, themselves a work of art made to lend wisdom and inspiration.
the Ægis: Many people expect religious rituals to be common in Ægis cities, which they are. What surprises them is that the worship is for each other and for their holy purpose, showing respect to the young, venerating the wise, and pledging service to the needy. The Ægis’ gods themselves participate in this worship. Most Shieldbearers can fly, so streets are sparsely populated, but the skyways are full and well-regulated. One might see light suddenly shine down from above as travelers receive messages from their godly patrons. There might initially seem to be no children outside, but that’s only because such a large percentage of their population is Sprung Full-Grown.
the Hearth-Kin: Hearth-kin space takes some getting used to. The vast hometrees are awe-inspiring, of course, but it's easier to get used to those than to the Hearth-Kin day-to-day. For instance, it's never really dark on a Hometree. It can be shadowy at night, but each tree is a tiny city-state with glowing fruits hanging from boughs, leaves reflecting the light back inward, and thousands of people with glowing eyes. Another good example is the blood magic. Nearly everyone on the street knows blood magic and uses it on a regular basis. You'll see people drawing their own blood, or helping someone else do it. No citizen thinks twice about letting a friend cut their thumb and draw in blood on their forehead - that's how their magic works.
Nova: Every sect of Nova is unique, and strongly, specifically unique. Whatever research is happening within that particular cult, it's going to tinge everything they do, and everyone's going to have a role in making it happen. Think beyond just Nature: no one investigates the entire Industry-nature. They research the conjuration of magical implements, or the structure of the Travel lattice, or creating faster methods of flight. A sect investigating the limits of cloning will be bringing in magical resources, building clone test facilities, implementing ways to handle multiple rituals at once, cloning themselves, and so forth. Another one might be looking into unorthodox uses of Guising. They'll be testing out how much "being a local" covers - navigation? Spying? Is it possible to intentionally break Guising or reverse it so as to spot spies? Some citizens might appear almost identical, others might have malfunctioning Guising and seem totally alien. Stretching the limits means embracing failure.
the Sovereigns: Ok, so there are demons, and the world is full of force and flash. Everyone knows that. What else? Sovereign language has no genders except in very intimate terms of address. When someone comes from a highly gendered civilization with gendered language, the True Speech simply elides pronouns. Sovereign language is also surprisingly non-hierarchical, with few terms of authority, submission, veneration, or even disrespect. In a culture where everyone considers themselves a ruler, subject to none, Sovereigns also gather primarily in small groups, because everyone involved is going to want to be heard and otherwise it takes too long to get anything done. Sovereigns are not patient people.
Those Above:
the Unroyal: The dream worlds the Unroyal inhabit are very different from those of Glimmermere. They are purposeful where Glimmermere is fanciful, cubist where Glimmermere is expressionist.
the Worldbuilders: When you come across another person during the day they're likely to be at work, many of them contributing to the rituals that call pieces of the city from the distant past. Those who aren't working on the city are likely teaching or taking care of children - most citizens raise children, whether their own or adopted. After work, many people have artistic hobbies - you'll see a lot of animated murals, walking statues, and impossible architecture. Many of these tie into the Worldbuilders' extensive fanfic archives. You're also likely to see a few spirits connected to the city, its structure, and its elements, moving about and directing the flow as needed to improve the city. Some people will be in elemental form, usually air or earth. The weather will never be too extreme, though during festivals it might be psychedelic.

Outside of Society

Some people leave society behind.

It's easy to walk away. There are no physical needs for which a reasonably magically educated adult cannot provide. If you want to go whole-hog, you can disconnect from Industry and never have a need in your life again, but most people don't choose that route. Spend a bit of Reserve and you can build a house, conjure non-perishable food, and keep most predators at bay.

What's harder for most people is leaving their friends behind. You always say you'll visit, you're never more than 5 koss away, there's the Universal Repositories if you want to write... but still, out of sight is out of mind for a lot of people, and everyone knows it. It's common for people to come back and invite friends to join them, or to gather a group of people and leave together. The human mind prefers a large circle of about 150 friends and acquaintances (depending on changes from Becoming), and most people leave with far fewer than that, leading to some difficult living situations.

Reasons for leaving vary. Some people decide they're morally opposed to their civilization's activities. This is most common amongst Diadem (especially the underclass) and the Sovereigns. Other people can't find the connection they want (Those Above, the Worldbuilders). Some people leave because they're badly depressed and they can't believe that anyone loves them or cares about them. It's not unheard-of for someone to leave from a lack of enthusaism for their civ's goals (Unroyal, Nova), but it's fairly rare. Most people who feel a litle burned out will stick around for their friends and just step back from the more intense activities.

If you come across someone in the wilderness who's left their civilization, things can vary a lot. Some people will recreate the sort of house they're used to from childhood. Others get creative with odd geometries and weird architecture, or houses built of flowers, or paths and roads made of shadow, or just plain moving into a Dream Realm. Most do some amount of foraging from the local environment. Some people prefer to live in the air, separate not only from their civilizations but from the Basin itself. Others walk hidden paths in the wilderness, never keeping a home, reconnecting with a natural world they felt distant from.

Nearly everyone who leaves picks up some sort of hobby. It's easy to get bored with no one around, or even if you live in a conclave of 20-50 people. Wherever people live, their hobbies will be visible. Some people play with the weather; their homes are easy to spot from far away thanks to the cloud patterns. Some carve wood or stone, leaving statues standing nearby. Some build homes close to ancient magitech devices, the better to study and perhaps even repair them. Even those who dabble in dreams will leave traces that the Sixth Sense can pick up on.

Most long-time hermits have lost interest in the niceties of polite society. What this means depends on what "polite society" meant in their previous homes. For the Hearth-Kin, it means they might not offer you food the moment you arrive, and might not ask about your troubles until you offer. For the Sovereigns, it means they might not bother to try insulting you, or they might have thrown aside their mask and robe to live with their bodies visible.

In game terms, leaving your civilization does not mean that you erase it from your character sheet. If the civ's Core Values are still part of you (very likely, you were raised here), then in game terms you're treated as if you're still part of that group. See Sorc page 15 for related details.

New Expressions

This section contains new Expressions for all six Natures. Each is suitable for selection as a Core Expression.

Our intention is that GMs may use the Arts in this book as story hooks and rewards for successful Archive expeditions. Each Art lists the place where it was discovered by the Archive before being placed in the Universal Repositories. GMs, feel free to adjust these as you see fit for your games. Let your players know which ones are available at game start and which must be discovered later. If you are uncertain as to which to choose, we recommend that Sea-work, Oath-taking, Psychotropics, and Splinching be widely known at the beginning of your game, and the rest be held back for discovery during play.

Notes

On Prerequisite Arts

Many of the Expressions in this book are advanced spells with a set of “Prerequisite Arts” listed. These are the magical techniques that must be available in order to cast those spells. One does not need to have the prerequisites as Core Expressions, but without them, the Art costs an extra point of Reserve for each prerequisite that is currently unavailable. Each point of Reserve represents an Expression being “spun up” and made available in order for the advanced spell to be cast.

List of Arts by Nature

Communion: Bonded Support, Entwined Objects
Industry: Boundless Transformation, Sea-work
Mystery: Judiciary Automata, Signature Ciphers, Stutter-stepping
Self: Oath-taking, Psychotropics, Shadow Familiars
Trickery: Aspect poisoning, Stutter-stepping
War: Hyperfighting, Splinching
Any: Miniscule Servitors

List of Arts by Type

Universal: None of the new arts are Universal.
Common: Entwined Objects, Oath-taking, Psychotropics
Restricted: Aspect poisoning, Bonded Support, Boundless Transformation, Hyperfighting, Judiciary Automata, Miniscule Servitors, Sea-work, Shadow Familiars, Signature Ciphers, Splinching, Stutter-stepping
Grand Wonderwork: None of the new arts are Grand Wonderworks. However, see the Broken Technologies section for mystic infrastructure that reached toward that level... and fell short.

List of Expressions

Aspect poisoning

Nature: Trickery
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: the Shell Game
Descriptors: Silent
Flow: Small
Common side effects: Chaotic flow

Most people are balanced with regard to the flow their bodies create. Aspect poisoning sets someone’s flow off-balance, shifting their Earthly Form to Aspected (Sorc page 20) or changing the aspect of those who are already Aspected. Because the change is sudden and unexpected, the effects are almost always negative.

Someone poisoned with the fire-aspect might burn things they touch. A ghost from the Cult poisoned with brightness might still be a ghost, but would find their body acting very differently and their now-light-aspected necromancy producing unexpected results. Aspect poisoning can spill over into the victim’s emotional states as well: a warrior “poisoned” with the aspect of peace would find it difficult to be violent, and a diplomat “poisoned” with laughter would struggle to lead effective negotiations.

Treat aspect poisoning much like curses, but with less vitriol and more satire.

This art was discovered in Worldbuilder territory, in the ruins of a perpetually darkened temple to a laughing, long-fanged god. It was incribed on a cylinder of obsidian, protected in layers of clay, bound with a seal so old that it crumbled before it could be read.

Bonded Support

Nature: Communion
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: Knotwork
Descriptors: Silent
Flow: Moderate
Common side effects: Emotional burn-in

Knotwork (Sorc, page 130) creates a loop of flow that anyone with the right Path can access at a later date, tying it into a physical object or pattern. Bonded support is similar, but it ties the loop into one person’s bond with another. When you pledge your bonded support to someone, you give them a one-time use of a Moderate amount of flow. They might decide to pass that flow on to someone else when they release the knot, but it cannot be stolen from them, and most people won’t even realize it’s there unless they’re looking for it.

Bonded support can be accessed from within Null Zones. No one can hold more than a Moderate amount of flow in bonded support, though they might hold Small amounts from multiple people. Much like knotwork, bonded support is often represented in physical form, as a small gift like jewelry or origami. It can also be given in less tangible forms, like poems or oaths. Some Geometers use tattoos from their friends to store their support again and again.

This art was discovered in Uinofa Thrice-Blessed, a Dream Realm of joy and forgiveness. It was gathered from the echoes that still ring in that place, pieced together through precognitive methods.

Boundless Transformation

Nature: Industry 4+
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: The Ten-Crore Stones of Death
Descriptors: Access, Loud
Flow: Large
Common side effects: Chaotic flow, Warped flow

The Ten-Crore Stones (Sorc page 143) destroy via transmutation, augmenting existing aspects of flow until light vaporizes stone or fear destroys thought. With a lighter touch, however, the Stones can be turned to more peaceful uses.

This Art uses a small amount of flow as a reference and retrofits large amounts of nearby matter to match. Presented with a handful of tiny gemstones, the Stones can turn a hillside into solid diamond. A breath, and winds carve a riverbed. A seedling grapevine can flood a field with ripe grapes ready for the picking, and a child’s warm blanket can engender whole cozy cottages. There are limitless applications.

It should be noted that, while the Industry-nature is not actively antagonistic toward living creatures in the way that the War-nature is, it does not take particular care around them either. Being overgrown with grapevines in a matter of seconds is an uncomfortable experience. Treat this as an attack with Nature equal to the caster’s Industry - 2 and use the Four Questions to resolve it.

There may also be novel applications of the Stones available via Mystery, Trickery, or Communion. Researchers are still working to uncover such arts.

This art was discovered inscribed upon one of the Stones themselves. The discoverer was transmuted to some unknown dense purple metal and plunged back to the Basin. Their recovery took years, but they never forgot the inscription.

Entwined Objects

Nature: Communion
Type: Common
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: Connection, Ritual
Flow: Trivial
Common side effects: Emotional burn-in

The term “entwined objects” is a misnomer. In truth, there is a single object in multiple places at the same time.

If the object is a book, the writing from one person is visible to all. If one is burned, they all are. If the object is an apple, when one person takes a bite it disappears from everyone’s. Coins dropped into an entwined jar are still only present for the person who put them in - it’s the jar that’s entwined, not the coins. If two people knowingly hold the same object, they have a mystic connection to each other.

Creating an entwined object that is person-sized or smaller is a Craft Ritual requiring Communion 2 and Theurge 2. Larger objects require longer Rituals. Living beings may start off entwined (e.g. if they are both created via Cloning), but will slowly become independent of one another.

This art was discovered in Geometer territory, in The Temples Of The Bowl. In these places, separated by thousands of miles, water from three springs pours endlessly into a single bowl. Its underside is incribed with the required chants and hand gestures to produce more.

Hyperfighting

Nature: War
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: Silent
Flow: Small
Common side effects: Emotional burn-in

Some Paths and Founts don’t lend themselves very well to War’s usual techniques. For more subtle (but no less effective) applications of War, a magus might call on precognitive flashes, extraordinary strategic thinking, or millions of years of honed instincts. Arete practitioners and Oneiromancers use this Art most frequently.

Hyperfighting doesn’t have the useful side-effects that other manifestations of War do, such as lighting a room with an energy blast or slicing a roast with extra-sharp weapons, but it’s easier to pass it off as ordinary to those who don’t know how to look.

This art was discovered in clay tablets, as part of an ancient style manual for a family of warrior-magi. Their enemies apparently discovered them and buried their city in volcanic ash. Lost before the age of immortality, their souls passed on long ago.

Judiciary Automata

Nature: Mystery
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: Mystic Servitors, Universal Repositories
Descriptors: Ex Nihilo, Ritual
Flow: Moderate
Common side effects: Emotional burn-in

The Brightgarden Schema, the Basin’s most widespread legal system, requires that rulings be recorded in as permanent a form as is readily available. Even in the pre-Gift era, that generally meant the Universal Repositories. Libraries worth of legal precedent and case law are stored there, if only one knows how to look. This Art creates an automaton that knows how to look.

Only simple legal rulings, where recorded precedent exists within the Brightgarden Schema, can be accessed. Even with this limitation, the Geometer’s Guild estimates that judiciary automata have cut down the demand on judges’ and lawyers’ time by over 40%, freeing them to work more conscientiously on more difficult cases.

This is a complex task for an automaton. Increase the ritual time by +1 time steps. The creator must have the Lawyer profession at 2+.

This art was invented by Flux of Nine Pines, of the Geometer’s Guild.

Miniscule Servitors

Nature: Varies
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: Mystic Servitors
Descriptors: Ex Nihilo, Ritual
Flow: Moderate
Common side effects: Flow depletion

Mystic Servitors are generally human-sized automata, but they don’t have to be. For example, some Worldbuilders create giant cranes and gantries to assist with construction. Smaller servitors are typically used as scouts, but some Nova researchers employ tiny creatures for microscopic investigations or adjustments, and some Hearth-kin nature-workers use armies of termites to build or demolish. Use the same guidelines from Sorc (page 132), with one “temporary servant” worth of miniscule servitors actually being anywhere between a hundred and several thousand.

As with regular mystic servitors, miniscule servitors’ abilities depend on the Nature one uses to create them. Communion servitors hold messages until someone walks by to hear them. Industry servitors build by moving millions of small pieces into place, though they’ll have trouble with heavier blocks. Those made with Mystery can see tiny things and sneak through small cracks (though big things are distorted to their senses). Trickery servitors can blind and confuse. War servitors can cut blood vessels and choke air passages. No one has yet found a use for tiny servitors of Self, but it is likely only a matter of time.

Thus far the smallest servitors are about the size of a flea. They must be constantly maintained with a Moderate amount of flow or they fall to pieces, but this cost will likely go down as the spells that create them are fine-tuned.

Initial attempts at this art were made by Nova Commonwealth researchers, but progress was only really made when they cross-referenced their work with records that the Archive was attempting to translate. Those were lifted from the bottom of the sea, in a trench held in stasis by exposure to elemental ice. The words were carved into the ice with letters fifty meters deep.

Oath-taking

Nature: Self
Type: Common
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: See below
Flow: Minimal
Common side effects: Emotional burn-in

One of the earliest arts children discover is to bind themselves to promises. (“I hereby pinky-swear that I will...”) It can come as a surprise to some when their very Self holds them to their word. Most adults grow out of this, but in some Traditions it is considered important or virtuous to take oaths.

Oath-taking works very much like Cursing oneself. Simply select the type of curse that will take effect and it will be so. Oaths are Silent (Sorc page 112) while they wait, but not when they are cast or when they act.

Oaths are not vicious or spiteful as curses are, but they are tenacious to a fault. To deny the oath, and refuse both to act in accordance and to take the curse, is to disconnect from Self.

Very few people have Oath-taking as a Core Expression. Instead, they spend a point of Reserve to swear a binding oath.

This art is common across the Basin.

Psychotropics

Nature: Self
Type: Common
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: None
Flow: Minimal
Common side effects: Emotional burn-in, Emotional fatigue

Psychotropic magic alters the caster’s perception and sense of reality. This art might use the expected powders, vapors, or mushrooms - but more esoteric methods exist, including warped mirrors, specialized meditation, gazing crystals, snuff made of solidified dreams, or ecstatic communion with the almighty Aion.

Mystical psychotropics are a scalpel compared to the hammer of natural mind-affecting substances. They can show the same vision every time, bring particular memories to the front, or engender specific feelings. They can be incredibly useful for those seeking a specific mindset, such as the benevolence of a healer or the calm of an Arete practitioner. Some uses can be as addictive as any drug, wearing deep channels in one’s mind and habits, blocking access to those emotions until the effect is applied again.

Psychotropics are a good opportunity to trigger the Worst Enemy Rule (Sorc pg 57), but can also be perfectly harmless or enjoyable. Using psychotropic arts on oneself is just a matter of describing the effect. Dosing someone else with a mystical drug uses the Hallucination art rather than this one.

Diadem takes credit for the recent development and popularization of this art, but there is ample evidence of its prior discovery and use elsewhere.

Sea-work

Nature: Industry
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: None
Flow: Varies
Common side effects: Warped flow

As Weather-working twists the skies and Nature-work bends plants and animals to the caster’s needs, Sea-work affects the ocean. It can change currents, ease winds, bring gales, swamp ships with waves, fend off creatures from the deep, or set those beasts against one’s enemies.

Sea-work’s control over the weather works exactly like Weather-working (Sorc page 149), except that it’s only effective on the shores of seas or tremendous lakes. Its control over animals and plants extends only to those that live underwater (or mostly so), and works like Nature-Working in those situations (Sorc page 133)

This art was reintroduced to the Basin by the Windblown (Sorc page 215), who claim to have kept it from an older culture. Investigations by the Archive show that this art must have been common amongst island-dwelling magi at one time.

Shadow Familiars

Nature: Self
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: Soul-work
Descriptors: Silent when hiding
Flow: None
Common side effects: None

To create a sentient creature to do one’s magical bidding, one must take it from one’s own self. Thus, the shadow familiar, or soul familiar. Shadow familiars are created by carefully cutting off a piece of one’s own soul, folding it origami-like into shape, and enchanting it with one’s own essence and psyche. They are always dark, often translucent, usually small and easily hidden. Many take the form of shadowy birds or snakes, and hide in wait in the magus’ own shadow until they are called forth.

Shadow familiars have Nature scores like any other character. Typically those scores are limited to the character’s own Natures (or lower), but occasionally they can be higher, such as when a low-magic character’s friends might enchant a powerful familiar to keep them safe. Use the higher of each score between the familiar and its owner when calculating Power and Import.

Many shadow familiars are disconnected from War and Industry, making them incapable of most physical interactions but also nearly untouchable. They use Self for quick movement and Trickery to steal. They seak and spy with Mystery and carry messages with Communion, which also keeps them in constant Rapport with their controller.

Necromancers are far more likely to be comfortable with the manipulation and enchantment of one’s own soul, making shadow familiars most common amongst the Sovereigns and the Cult. Members of the Soulpact often risk a piece of their own soul this way, to have a companion in their difficult and sometimes lonely work.

The GM should let characters with this Expression play their own familiar. It is, after all, nothing more than an extension of their own Self. Losing a shadow familiar is exactly like losing a piece of one’s own soul - see Sorc page 146.

This art was held by the Black Sand Architects, a culture of ghosts who predeceased the Cult of the Empty Grave and are now typically considered part of their civilization. They taught it willingly to the Archive when asked.

Familiar or Friend?

Familiars are a staple of fantasy literature and folk tales - a witch’s cat, a warlock’s imp, doing their bidding and helping them with magical rituals. In the Great Basin, of course, the Gift makes it impossible to bend sentient creatures to one’s will. When one sees an imp working with a Sovereign, that imp acts under duress, but not under some magical geas. When one of the Hearth-Kin walks by with a bird whispering secrets into their ear, that creature is their friend, not their servant.

Signature Ciphers

Nature: Mystery
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: Silent, sometimes Uncast
Flow: None
Common side effects: None

By using both your magical signature (Sorc page 96) and the signature of someone you know, you can encode a written message so that only the two of you can read it. Someone who knows both signatures and knows that this message is encoded with those two in particular can break the cipher. Otherwise, the message is nothing but a strange set of jumbled symbols laid atop one another - recognizable as a coded message to someone who knows this art, but unreadable. Psychometry used on the message can sometimes give hints as to who created it.

Encoding or decoding a written message with a signature cipher takes a few seconds if there is cryptic or secretive flow available. However, it can also be done by hand, without magic, in about an hour per page.

This art comes from an archaeological dig in the Worlds Beyond, beneath a city built on ever-older, ever-more-complex strata of technomagic. The Golden Ægis claim this place now, but the Archive’s explorations were there first.

Splinching

Nature: War 3+
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: None
Descriptors: Connection, Loud
Flow: Moderate
Common side effects: Chaotic flow

Travel is the closest thing the Basin has ever discovered to safe long-range teleportation. Note the operative word “safe.” Splinching deploys one of the hundreds of not-so-safe methods against one’s enemy.

When this Art inflicts lower-level Complications, it only removes small pieces or disorients someone. Higher-level Complications can leave someone halfway across the Basin, in one piece or in thousands.

This art is less a “discovery” and more a byproduct of many unfortunate failures.

Stutter-stepping

Nature: Mystery or Trickery
Type: Restricted
Prerequisite arts: the Red Space or Spirit-walking or Transubstantiation
Descriptors: Loud
Flow: Small
Common side effects: Chaotic flow, Emotional fatigue

A primarily defensive technique, stutter-stepping phases one’s body intermittently through a different dimension or state of being. Attacks often pass through empty space where the body was less than a second ago. Stutter-stepping does allow its practitioners to pass through solid walls, but they are still somewhat vulnerable to poison gas or other environmental effects.

All methods for stutter-stepping cary some degree of danger over the long term, so no one lives this way - at least, no one who’s healthy and sane.

This art was found on a cache of materials retrieved from the Red Space. The Archive plumbed an entire square meter of Basin space where ancient statues pointed to a potentially lost or trapped object or entity. They finally drew forth many common items, among which was carpet scratched with this spell via a knife or other sharp implement.

Useful References

Mystic Connections

Every magical art with the Connection descriptor:

Dream Travel
Enchantment
Entwined Objects
Farspeech
Healing
Lagged Curses
Mnemosurgery
Nightmare_Exile
Precognition
Rapport
Soul-work
Splinching

Arts that benefit from a mystic connection:

Energy Waves
Sixth Sense
Travel
the Uncountable Spinners

Loud and Silent

Loud arts:

Boundless Transformation
Enchantment
Energy Waves
the Red Space
Splinching
Stutter-Stepping
the Ten-Crore Stones
Terror
Travel

Silent arts:

Bonded Support
Curses
Dream Travel (usually)
Guising
Hyperfighting
Hypnopraxis
Lagged Curses
Mental Acuity (usually)
Personae
Shadow Familiars (usually)
the Shell Game
the Shroud
Signature Ciphers
the Sixth Sense
Spirit-Walking
the Uncountable Spinners
the Universal Repositories

Aspects for the Arts

Almost every art needs a particular type of flow in order to work. In the Sorc corebook, we generally leave it up to the GM and players as to what aspects, emotions, or mindsets make sense, only noting a few oddballs (like life-flow not mattering for Healing). If you’d like a little more structure, here are a few Aspects for each of the game’s many Arts.

In most cases, these aspects can come from outside the magus or from within. They also don’t need to be permanent emotional conditions: you can empty your mind to use Deconjuration, and in the heat of battle you will probably find the violent flow needed to cast an energy wave. Changing emotions regularly or staying in one mindset for a long period of time can trigger emotional side-effects, as mentioned for many of these arts.

Consider this a partial list of possibilities, not a comprehensive set of rules or a set of absolute requirements. Be generous in interpreting different aspects. Go with what feels right to the character and their Tradition.

Aspect poisoning: Imbalance, poison, irony, tides
Becoming: Becoming works with any aspect of flow, though it is faster when the available aspects match the changes to be made.
Bonded Support: Friendship, love, faith, secrecy, desperation
Boundless Transformation: Surrender, planning, harmony - plus, of course, the aspect to be cloned.
the Burning Dream: Fire, chaos, destruction, structure
Cloning: Pairing, growth, reflection, envy, clay
Conjuration: Any type that matches the object to be conjured. Examples:

For wine: a piece of grapevine, a memory of grape jam, another kind of wine, thirst
For a tool: Work, precision, the material of which the tool is made
For a mask: Cloth or ceramic as appropriate, deception, fun

Curses: Anger, spite, cruelty, poison
Deconjuration: Void, empty-mind, hunger
Distillation: Mental concentration and focus, wealth, structure
Dream Travel: Dreams, escape, worry, adventure, courage
Dreamshaping: Inspiration, desire, megalomania, play, treasure
Enchantment: Friendship, braiding, protection, raising, plus whatever the original Expression would require.
Energy Waves: Violence, passion, focus, energy of the appropriate type, a damaged object
Entwined Objects: Reflection, family, yearning, truth
Expanded Expertise: Does not require flow. The act of acquiring Expanded Expertise might require all sorts of different flow, but it varies greatly by type, Path, and Fount.
Farspeech: Loneliness, friendship, concern, gossip
Guising: Guising pulls exactly the aspects it needs from its surroundings. Trying to feed it something else breaks it.
Hallucination: Enjoyment, concealment, confusion, passion
Healing: Benevolence, kindness, well-wishing
Hyperfighting: Calm, focus, fury, panic
Hypnopraxis: Persistence, obsession, restlessness
Immortality: Immortality’s flow comes entirely from the mage’s own body and sense of self.
Judiciary Automata: Wisdom, rules, pedantry, information
Knotwork: Preparedness, greed, pattern, rotation
Lagged Curses: As per regular curses, plus: deviousness, patience, obsession
Mental Acuity: Pattern, mathematics, artistry, puzzles. Mental acuity cannot take its flow from the mage themselves - they are already as smart as they will be without assistance.
Minuscule Servitors: As per Mystic Servitors, plus as small a thing (physical or emotional) as the caster can perceive or imagine.
Mnemosurgery: Precision, forgetfulness, preservation, impermanence
Multitasking: Persistence, obsession, restlessness, or a myriad of flows woven together
Mystic Servitors: Varies by type and intended purpose.
Nature-Work: The presence of natural environments (as opposed to things shaped by hand or by other magics) is a requisite for this sort of magic. Growing things are common, but decaying things are part of nature too.
Nightmare Exile: Indifference, ennui, spite, delirium
Null Tolerance: None
Oath-taking: Desire, trust, linkage, blood
Personae: Reflection, masks, deception, play. These are only required when the persona is initially raised, not while it is active.
Physical Prowess: Solidity, flexibility, vigor, machinery, animal aspects. Physical prowess cannot take its flow from the mage themselves - they are already as strong as they will be without assistance.
Precognition: Time, bells, resonance, echoes
Psychometry: Mist, dissection, clarity, trance states
Psychotropics: Existing drugs and medicines, ecstatic states, aspects tied to the type of result that is desired.
Rapport: Love, compassion, togetherness, friendship, pairing
the Red Space: Concealment, hunger, misdirection
Sea-work: The presence of large amounts of sea- and salt-flow and natural environments (as opposed to things shaped by hand or by other magics) is a requisite for this sort of magic.
Shadow Familiars: Darkness, trust, servitude
Shapeshifting: Flow appropriate to the form attained. Because the flow must come from within the character’s body, the required emotional state reflects the character’s cultural metaphors (e.g. the turtle is a creature of determination for the Guild, but one of hesitation and fear for Diadem).
the Shell Game: Treachery, deception, craftiness. As mentioned in this Expression’s description, this cannot come from within the person running the game – it must be drawn from outside.
the Shroud: Stealth, fear, audacity, silence, caution
Signature Ciphers: Stealth, deception, mathematics, protection, confusion
Sixth Sense: Introspection, alertness, lenses, concentration. Note that the Sixth Sense does not require any flow at all for nearby objects.
Soul-Work: Shadows, precision, artistry, compassion
Sovereignty: None
Spirit-Walking: Varies by Tradition and Fount, as appropriate to their style of spirit-walking.
Splinching: Cruelty, division, destruction
Stutter-stepping: As per the caster’s approach to Spirit-Walking or the Red Space, whichever they use as a prerequisite for this art.
Tailored Canon: Craftiness, pedantry, artistry, selfishness
Telekinesis: Strength, focus, rage, wind
the Ten Crore Stones of Death: Anger, bleakness, severity, devotion, arrogance, plus the aspect chosen to catastrophically augment.
Terror: Rage, cold, fear, despair, intimidation
Transcendence: Flow appropriate to the new Earthly Form.
Transmutation: An appropriate flow for the new material.
the Travel Lattice: Persistence, hustle, connection, yearning
True Speech: Communication, trust, intrigue
the Uncountable Spinners of Silver Thread: Reverence, connection, permanence, cycles
Universal Repositories: Learning, literature, curiosity
Warding: Protection, caution, paranoia, durability
Weaponry: Danger, anger, determination
Weather-working: Passion, water, wind, calm, artistry

Emotional Aspects in Objects

Emotionally-aspected flow doesn’t need to come from people. Objects can have imbued aspects (Sorc page 95) that provide emotional resonance. A set of ringing bowls long used for calming meditation will have that aspect imprinted on them. They can provide the calm necessary to activate Hyperfighting to any user, even if the caster’s culture makes no use of ringing bowls at all.

Traditions that believe in inherent symbolism (those that access Alchemy, Earthpower, or Elementalism) can also provide emotional aspects from pure manifestations of certain materials or forces. An alchemist with a vial of mercury might tap it for its aspect of speed for Physical Prowess. An Earthpower adept might access the art of Belonging with an acorn, using aspects of growth and potential.

It’s ok to invent these associations for your Tradition as you go along, but it’s also a good idea to write them down so that you don’t contradict yourself later.